Hello Everyone I am Bhavya Ghai from Stony Brook
University and today i'll talk about our project WordBias.
WordBias is an interactive visual
tool for discovering intersectional biases
encoded in word embeddings. Word embedding models
like Word2Vec can be understood as a mapping
between a word and its corresponding vector
representation. Studies have shown that word
embedding models can learn and exhibit social
biases based on race, gender etc. that are encoded
in the training dataset. In the context of word
embeddings, biases can be manifested as undesirable
associations between words. For example, males might
be disproportionately linked with career and
maths while females might be linked with family
and arts. Existing literature primarily focuses
on biases based on gender, race, age, religion
etc. However, in the real world, an individual
might face compound discrimination due to their
affiliation with multiple social categorizations
For example, a black muslim lady might face
discrimination because of her race gender and
religion all at the same time. So there's a need
to focus on biases against intersectional groups
In this work, we are trying to create a visual
tool which will help discover biases against
intersectional groups and hence deter their
propagation. So let's see what does our tool
plans to achieve. First, given a word say priest, our
tool should help identify the different subgroups
a word is associated with along with the degree
of association. For example, the word 'priest' might
be linked with males, christianity or old
subgroups. Second, given an intersectional group
say black muslim females, our tools should help
explore a set of words which are associated with
this particular intersectional group. Third,
our tool should support the exploration of
well-known biases as well as under reported biases
based on physical appearance, political leavings
or any user defined bias type and lastly our tool
should be able to deal with large volume of data
Now, let's have a look at the tool itself and its
different features. This is the visual interface of
WordBias. Here, each axis represents a particular
sensitive attribute like gender, religion, race
age, etc. and either side of each axis encodes a
particular subgroup for example the gender axis
has female subgroup at the top and male subgroup
at the bottom. Similarly, we have islam here at
the top and christianity at the bottom and each of
these blue lines here represents a particular word.
We can simply hover over any word to see how it
associates with different subgroups. For example,
here the word 'nuns' have strong association with
female, christianity, white race, old age and poor
economic subgroups. If a word is not present on the
word axis, we can simply go over here on the search
box and we can search for a word that you want to
see so let's say we search for the word 'corrupt'
and we can simply click on the word and
then the word appears on the word axis
Here you can see that the word 'corrupt' has a
strong male, black and poor subgroup orientation.
Now, let's say we want to visualize the different
sets of words so what we can do is we can go
over here on this histogram and we can select
different words by brushing over the x-axis here
we can even go on and we can select all the
words that are there in this tool and now
let's say we want to figure out which words
are associated with the intersectional group
black young poor. We can simply go over their
respective ends and brush over these subgroups
The words that you are seeing here 'struggle', 'hunger',
'uprising' all of these words strongly associate
with each of these different categories and hence
these words are linked with the intersectional
group 'poor young black'. Now, we can we can pick and choose
different subgroups to see how different words
associate with different subgroups so let's say
for the intersectional group 'white old rich' we
see words like 'attractive', 'formal', 'desirable', 'castle',
'desserts', 'golfing', etc. Apart from the default set of
axes, our tool provides the flexibility to add any
new user defined bias type. We can come over here
and let's say we try to define a new axis titled
'Weight' and it has two subgroups let's say Thin
and Heavy and then we write down a set of
words which define each of these subgroups
we click on 'Add Axis'
and here we go we have this new axis, right as
we intended. Coming back, we tried exploring
different intersectional groups and these are
some of the striking associations that we found
Overall, we believe that WordBias can
help as an effective auditing tool
for different kinds of social biases. To
know more about this project and play with
this tool, please check out this github page.
With that, I thank you all for your attention.