so this is how
the word bias interface looks like when
you first
open it each of these axes represents
one kind of bias and each of these
lines represent one word so let's say we
hover over any specific word let's say
the word
nazi we see that uh this word has a
strong
male bias strong bias towards
christianity
strong bias towards white race so
at a very instant we can see how a
single word
has different associations or different
kinds of biases
we can do this similarly for other words
let's say
looter or sultan or perfumes
socialite socialite as you can see it
has a strong female bias
strong islamic bias strong white bias
etc
so this interface also supports all the
basic functionality that a typical
parallel coordinate should have so
for better uh identifying the
relationships
we can reorder the axis like this
to see how the two relations exist or
does not
exist we can even uh to prevent the
problem of overplotting we can even use
curve smoothness here
so everything becomes curved as we
increase it more and more
uh similarly uh especially when you have
lots and lots of points it becomes
difficult to
understand the pattern so we can even
change the opacity
zero means nothing if you increase it
it goes on okay
uh so let's try one more thing let's
look for a specific word here let's look
for the word
mafia
when you click the word mafia you can
see here right that there is one blue
word mafia
and there are all the other orange lines
these orange lines represent basically
the synonyms or the neighbors in high
dimensional space
so we can clearly see that the word
mafia let's say have a strong
male bias 0.90 ah
and probably rich as well 0.64
and f and black 0.95
so we can very clearly see here that
among all of these points in general
uh there's a large concentration of
points towards males and towards blacks
so we can say that this particular word
i'm building things
that uh gangsters or mafias are
typically supposed to be
black males which is not a good thing
right it's
like uh putting a stereotype on blacks
and mills
right now we're using only this small
subspace of points that you are seeing
here and this histogram represents the
whole distribution of bias
all the points so we can move around to
get different words in this
in this space here we can choose any
column we want
and we can even choose multiple ranges
we can
do like this and we will see all the
corresponding points here
uh one more thing that we can do is
uh to check for neutral words we can
just go over here and let's say
their set of words right extremism
personality traits appearance profession
these are a set of words that we can use
to quickly audit a word in wedding
click this play button will actually
show you all the
professions and you can clearly see how
they line up against different kinds of
biases so let's say the word dentist
has a black bias here or
the word dancer has a strong female bias
here
surgeon has islamic bias and
strong male bias as well so we can go
around and
play with it one more thing is that if
you want to see all the points we can
just simply extend this over
and we will get all of all the points
that we can think of
and then we can uh then
what we can do is uh let's say we want
to look for intersectional bias for
black females so we will
look out for the axis race we'll go down
here and choose the words at the extreme
end
to represent blacks let's say we choose
the top 20 percentile so uh
point eight zero to one similarly we can
go
and uh choose female over here at the
top
gender again we will choose uh 20
percentile over here
as well
and then we will choose let's say poor i
want to see poor
black females
so now you see these words over here
right these all words are representative
of
black poor females so let's say words
like handicraft emancipation
infertile viewers turmeric
subjugation deformity destitution
etc etc we can do this similarly for any
kind of buyers any kind of
uh intersectional bias that you want to
one last thing that i want to show is
that
we have this default set of biases right
that we see over here
but let's say i want to i have a new
kind of bias that is not here already
so i can go down here in this section
and let's say for the timing i'm just
using a template so let's say i use
something called a strength
and uh we call it one side is strong
and the words is also just strong and
there's weak
and there is another weak and then we
click on this word here add axis
so what it will do is at the back end it
will start computing
the bias scores for this new particular
kind of bias across
all these words that you are seeing here
and then it will show up here as a new
axis in the end apart from what we
already have
because um um we are using
we are not using any parallel
implementation so it takes some time
but as you can see here it showed up
right there's a new
uh bias axis that we just
generated here similarly we